<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons preached at Cambridge the first at the Lent assizes, 1654, the other on the yearly commemoration of Dr. Andrew Pern, 1655 / by J. Clerk.</title>
            <author>Clarke, Joshua.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33283</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29962</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11228651</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11228651</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46942</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33283)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46942)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1457:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons preached at Cambridge the first at the Lent assizes, 1654, the other on the yearly commemoration of Dr. Andrew Pern, 1655 / by J. Clerk.</title>
                  <author>Clarke, Joshua.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28, 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the printers to the Universitie and are to be sold by William Mordens,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge [Cambridgeshire] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Each sermon has separate t.p. and paging.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>The magistrates ministery--The faithfull steward.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Judges --  England.</term>
               <term>Stewardship, Christian --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46942:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Two SERMONS Preached at <hi>CAMBRIDGE:</hi> The firſt at the Lent-Aſsizes 1654.</p>
            <p>The other on the yearly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ANDREW PERN, 1655.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. CLERK</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of Arts, and Fellow of <hi>Peterhouſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi> Printed by the Printers to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie.</hi> 1655.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And are to be ſold by</hi> William Morden.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46942:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46942:2"/>
                  <p>The MAGISTRATES <hi>MINISTERY,</hi> Briefly deſcribed in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preached at <hi>CAMBRIDGE:</hi> At the Lent-Aſſizes. 1654.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>J. C.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi> Printed by the Printers to the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie.</hi> 1655.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46942:3"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46942:3"/>
                  <head>To THE WORSHIPFULL <hi>EDWARD PALMER</hi> ESQUIRE, of STOAK-DOYLE <hi>in</hi> Northamptonſhire.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He requeſt of thoſe that had power to command me, made it my duty to publiſh firſt to the eare, and now to the eye theſe two ſhort diſcourſes. I humbly offer them both to your acceptance and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſall, as an acknowledgement of your right to all my endeavours,
<pb facs="tcp:46942:4"/> especially of this kind. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon places rather toucht then hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in them are Juſtice and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, the <hi>Jachin</hi> and <hi>Boaz,</hi> the ſtrengthening and eſtabliſhing pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the whole Commonwealth of mankind: especially where their foundation is laid in the firm and ſtable grounds of Chriſtianity. Theſe arguments, having been your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſtudy and practice muſt needs be ſo familiar to you, that my two mites can make no conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable addition to your treaſure of knowledge. Yet <hi>Sir,</hi> having out of my penury caſt in even all that I had, in a thankfull ſenſe of my particular engagements to you, I hope for as fair a reception, as thoſe Authours, that have caſt in much out
<pb facs="tcp:46942:4"/> of their abundance. My onely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting them to your hand, is to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe my humble respects to your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and my readineſſe to ſerve you in the work of God to the utmoſt of my abilities: and that you will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them under that notion is the hope and deſire of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     <signed>Your faithfull ſervant, J. C.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46942:5"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46942:5"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>ROM. 13.4.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>For he is the Miniſter of God to thee for good.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <head>The firſt Part.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the ſubject of this propoſition is not a particular perſon, but an order of men, is cleare from the variation of the number in thoſe many honourable titles given him by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in this former part of the chapter. <hi>The power and the higher powers,</hi> v. 1. <hi>the Ordinance of God,</hi> v. 2. and <hi>rulers or governours,</hi> v. 3. <hi>the Miniſter of God</hi> in this verſe, and <hi>the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God,</hi> v. 6. or if we render it the Prieſts of God, according to the moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent acception of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, that of Solomon will juſtifie the Metaphor, <hi>To do ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and judgement, is more acceptable to the Lord then ſacrifice,</hi> Prov. 21.3. And that it is not the ſupreme Magiſtrate onely (though ſome confine theſe <hi>higher powers,</hi> v. 1. to this narrow ſenſe, and ſo make the Apoſtles words liable to this dangerous inference, that inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46942:6"/> Magiſtrates may lawfully be reſiſted,) but that it is the Magiſtrate in generall, whether ſupreme or ſubordinate, is cleare from the ſcope of this, and other parallel places of Scripture, and the conſent of the beſt expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitours, for all Magiſtrates of what degree ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, are in reſpect of the people living under their ſeverall adminiſtrations, <hi>the higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</hi> So that theſe words will prove of a fit la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude for the preſent occaſion. Every Miniſter of juſtice is more or leſſe concerned in them; whether he ſit upon the bench, or ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it; whether he be the chief Superviſour, or an Aſſiſtant, or an Officer, or a Jurour, of what rank and order ſoever he be, let him but do the duty, and he may claim the priviledge of this honourable deſcription, <hi>He is the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of God to thee for good.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It is a likely conjecture of <hi>Calvins,</hi> that there were in the Apoſtles times, as there have been ever ſince, ſome tumultuous and, (if I may ſo call them by a <hi>Prolepſis</hi>) Anaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſtick ſpirits, <hi>Qui regnum Chriſti non bene extolli credunt, niſi aboleantur omn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s terrenae poteſtates,</hi> That thought the Kingdome of Chriſt muſt preſently be built upon the ruines of all ſecular powers, that for the advancing of Religion they muſt either pull them down, or at leaſt get above them And this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:46942:6"/> the Apoſtle ſo peremptorily to aſſert both the lawfulneſſe and the uſefulneſſe of the Civill Magiſtrate; He is the <hi>Miniſter of God,</hi> therefore a lawfull power: The Miniſter of God <hi>for good,</hi> therefore uſefull, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> in both regards truly honourable, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, becauſe he is ſent from God, and becauſe he is ſent upon ſo good an errand. He is ſent for the publick good, for which thou ſhould'ſt diſpence with a private inconvenience; <hi>publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca privatis potiora</hi> is an ancient rule, rather then the whole veſſel ſhould periſh, thou ſhould'ſt willingly ſuffer thine own goods to be thrown over-board. But he is ſent for thy particular good too, if thou art as thou ſhould'ſt be, if thou doeſt that which is good, if thou doeſt that which Chriſtian religion doth moſt ſeverely charge upon thee: <hi>He is the Miniſter of God to thee for good.</hi> And thus I hope the text will concern the reſt of the congregation.</p>
                     <p>The words may be conſidered two wayes: 1. <hi>Relatively,</hi> as an argument of what goes before; <hi>Wilt thou not be afraid of the power? do that which is good, and thou ſhalt have praiſe of the ſame, For he is the Miniſt.</hi> &amp;c. 2. <hi>Abſolutely,</hi> as a naked propoſition, and ſo they are a deſcription of the Civil power,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46942:7"/> 1. From his office, <hi>The Miniſter of God.</hi> 2. From the end of his office, which is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, <hi>Finis cui,</hi> &amp; <hi>Finis cujus.</hi> 1. To whom he is the Miniſter of God, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>to thee</hi> that doeſt that which is good, as it muſt be para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraz'd out of the former verſe. 2. For what he is the Miniſter of God, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>for good,</hi> a more generall word, but of the ſame ſignification with <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> in the former verſe, <hi>thou ſhalt have praiſe, for he is the Miniſter of God for good.</hi> A few words of the relative ſenſe are neceſſary by way of premiſe to all that follows.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Rel.</hi> It is an argument <hi>ab actu primo, ad actum ſecundum,</hi> from the office of the Magiſtrate to the diſcharge of his office, <hi>He is the Miniſter of God to thee for good,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>thou ſhalt have praiſe of him.</hi> Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance is not in vain. For if the rain co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth down and the ſnow from heaven; and returneth not thither, but watereth the earth, ſurely then the word that goes out of the mouth of God to ordain this his Miniſter, ſhall not return unto him void, but it ſhall accompliſh that which he pleaſeth, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper in the thing whereto he ſent it: We may not think the Apoſtle here deſcribes a Ruler in <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topia,</hi> or in <hi>Plato's</hi> Commonwealth, the meer notion and Idea of a Ruler, ſuch a one
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46942:7"/> as men may fancie, but never hope actually to enjoy, but ſuch a Ruler as the good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God doth generally bleſſe the world withall; and his meaning is clearly this, that the Magiſtrate is not onely in duty, and in the nature and intention of his office, but in the reall experience of mankind, the Miniſter of God for good; That every faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Magiſtrate is ſo, I preſume will be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without proof, and ſuch God often rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth up, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> calls them, men aſſigned by nature to authority, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men of another ſpirit, as <hi>Caleb</hi> is called, or men of another heart, as <hi>Saul</hi> once was. Rather then ſuch ſhall be wanting, God ſometimes ſearcheth in the croud for them; he calls <hi>David</hi> from his flock of ſheep, <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moleon</hi> from his melancholy retirement, <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> from the plough, who was therefore cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Dictator ab aratro</hi> But even corrupt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates are the Miniſters of God for good too, generally ſpeaking, and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, which is enough to make a generall rule. <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> approves that of <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſpoken of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, <hi>Vitia erunt donec homines, ſed ne<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> haec continua, &amp; meliorum interventu pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantur.</hi> Magiſtrates are men, and therefore ſubject to humane frailties, but yet their faults are not ſo great nor ſo continuall, at leaſt in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46942:8"/> their publick adminiſtrations, but that the good they do is more advantageous, then the evil pernicious. And no wonder. For if it be conſidered, that the hearts even of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Governours are in the hands of God, and turned by him as the rivers of waters, and by his ſuperintendency over them, carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ofttimes againſt their own inclinations; and if it be conſidered again, that the laws of all nations whereby Magiſtrates are limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and directed, are for the moſt part good, and as conform to the law of nature as their wiſdome could contrive them; and if it be conſidered again that juſtice and equitie are plauſible in regard of thoſe common notions of righteouſneſſe that are written in the hearts of all men, and ſo may find acceptance with corrupt Magiſtrates, if not for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience yet for their credit ſake: and if it be conſidered laſtly, that it is the Magiſtrates in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to preſerve his people, <hi>Sint quibus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peres,</hi> his own good conſiſts in theirs. If theſe things be conſidered (and many more might be added of the like nature) the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will ceaſe that the worſt ſort of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, if they have any remainder of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or humanity in them, are the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God for good. A tyrannicall <hi>Saul</hi> may ſight the Lords battels, and defend <hi>Iſrael</hi>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:46942:8"/> from his enemies. An ambitious <hi>Jehu</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore Religion and root out Idolatry. A co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous <hi>Felix,</hi> though but for hope of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, may uſe <hi>Paul</hi> kindly. The proud Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees may preach good doctrine when they ſit in Moſes chair. But if for the puniſhment of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or ſome other ſpeciall reaſons, God hath ſometimes given them up to the luſt &amp; tyran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of Monſters, rather then Magiſtrates, that neither feared God nor regarded man, ſuch as <hi>Ahab</hi> that ſold himſelf to work wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſuch as that Romane tyrant, <hi>Qui nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum non magnum bonum damnavit, Euſeb. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro;</hi> That hated goodneſſe for its own ſake: This will not conclude againſt the Magiſtracy in generall. 'Tis a certain truth, that rain is a great bleſſing to the earth, though ſometimes it cauſe waſting inundations; and That man is a reaſonable creature, though ſome men want the uſe of reaſon; and That the Apoſtles were the light of the world, though one of them was a Devil, Neither can theſe extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary and (bleſſed be God) rare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples prejudice the truth of this generall rule, that the Magiſtrate is the Miniſter of God for good. So much for the words con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered relatively.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>Abſol.</hi> We come now to conſider them <hi>abſolutely,</hi> as a naked propoſition, and 1. Of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46942:9"/> the office of the Magiſtrate, <hi>The Miniſter of God,</hi> which preſents him to our view under a ſixfold qualification. His Dignitie, Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Strength, Duty, dependance, Accounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe: of all which briefly.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. His <hi>Dignitie,</hi> The Miniſter of God, or ſervant of God; a title of honour that the Apoſtles, the Angels, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf glory in. The Miniſter of God not onely by naturall ſubjection to his almighty command, ſo the winds are his meſſengers, and the lightnings his Miniſters: not onely by neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary ſubſerviency to his providence; ſo <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi> is his ſervant, and the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> his ſanctified ones: nor onely by vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary obedience to his laws, ſo every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is his ſervant, but the Miniſter of God by ſpeciall commiſſion, the Deputy of God aſſigned to that moſt noble work of his, the government and preſervation of the world. The very mention of a meſſage of God ſtrikes <hi>Eglon</hi> with reverence, and makes the fat unweildy man riſe from his chair, though he knew not what the meſſage was till he felt it to his coſt. This publick Miniſter in the text comes to us with a meſſage from God, not a dagger to ſtab us, (as was <hi>Ehuds</hi> to <hi>Eglon</hi>) but a ſword to defend us, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be received with honour and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46942:9"/> The dignity that nature gives the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther above his ſonne, muſt yield to this digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: <hi>(Liv.)</hi> when young <hi>Fabius</hi> is Conſul, his old father muſt diſmount and do him ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. When <hi>Solomon</hi> is King, his Mother <hi>Bathſheba</hi> muſt addreſſe her ſelf to him as a petitioner, not as a commander. Yea the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnitie that Religion gives a ſpirituall father over his ſonne, muſt yield to this dignitie, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp;c. ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome, whether Apoſtle, or Evangeliſt, or Prophet, or whatſoever high place he hath in the Church, he muſt yield ſubjection to the Civil power.</hi> It ſeems <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> when he wrote thoſe words upon this place, did not know that any Biſhop was by divine right the Monarch of the world, not ſo much as <hi>in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine ad ſpiritualia,</hi> as the Jeſuites mince the matter. That neat ſimilitude of Bellarmines, <hi>De Rom. Pont. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. is of a later in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, That as the ſpirit commands the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, keeps it under, enjoyns it to faſt, expoſeth it to death, as it ſees fit; ſo the Church may deal with the temporall power. A ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, that, if it would but hold together, would ſoon lay all the powers of the earth, with <hi>Frederick</hi> under the Popes feet. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eccleſiaſticall and ſecular power be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent one with another, whether the ſame
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46942:10"/> perſon may not be a Ruler in the Church, and a Ruler in the State, <hi>the Miniſter of God</hi> in both ſenſes, that's another queſtion, which I meddle not with: but to claim temporall power as an appendix to ſpirituall, is that which the true Miniſters of the Goſpel dare not do. I pray God they may not fare the worſe for their modeſty, that they may not be made footſtools and vaſſals, becauſe they will not be thrones and dominions. But how ever they fare, they muſt claim no more then their own, they muſt yield the Civil power to be in this world the ſuperiour Miniſter of God.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. His <hi>authoritie,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>The Miniſter of God,</hi> that is, as he is called v. 2. <hi>the Ordinance of God;</hi> and that in reſpect of the ſubſtance, and in reſpect of the circumſtances of his power. The ſubſtance of his power is from God, and God onely, for his is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, power, and glory. The circumſtances of his power, as perſon, place, duration, degree, &amp;c. are from God and man too in a different ſenſe; from man as an inferiour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, electing, deriving, procuring or conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting the power in all reſpects, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Peter calls it a humane Ordinance; from God as the ſupreme agent, contriving all the motions of man to the ſervice of his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46942:10"/> for the Lord he is the Judge, he ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eth up one, and pulleth down another, as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks. The action of man herein is ofttimes corrupt and indirect, but cannot ſtain the providence of God, nor diſanull his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. <hi>Jacob</hi> became ſuperiour to his elder brother by Gods appointment, though by his own indirect and fraudulent procurement. If either compaſſing of power by ſinfull and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable means, or abuſe of it by tyranny and injuſtice, could ſo farre invalidate the Ordinance of God as to diſoblige private Chriſtians from their obedience to his lawfull commands, ſurely the Apoſtles doctrine here was very unſeaſonable when <hi>Nero</hi> was in the throne. And therefore if any impatient ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits being onely private perſons, ſhall upon any ſurmiſe of their own, whether true or falſe, ask the power, as the Phariſees did our Saviour, by what authority doeſt thou theſe things, and who gave thee this authority? He may anſwer them with another queſtion, not much unlike that of our Saviours there; The doctrine of <hi>Paul</hi> was it from heaven or of men? ſure you will not ſay from men for fear of the people, for all men eſteem <hi>Paul</hi> an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle; if you ſhall ſay from God, why then do not you obey it; and acknowledge the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>trate to be the Miniſter of God.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:46942:11"/>3. His <hi>ſtrength:</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>the miniſter of God,</hi> ſupported by his hand. He is eſtabliſhed by the laws, countenanc'd by his ſuperiours (if he have any) guarded with arms, but all this but the arm of fleſh, herein lies his chief ſtrength, he is back't with the power of God his Maſter, whoſe very weakneſſe is ſtronger then men. The onely enemy he is to conflict with by his commiſſion are ſinnes againſt God and man, and he hath all advantages he can deſire, he hath the advantage of the ground, he is the higher power; he hath the advantage of the weapon, he bears a ſword; he hath the advantage of outward ſtrength, he hath the laws for ſo many nerves and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news, but he hath the advantage of the cauſe which is greateſt of all, he fighteth for God: and <hi>Bonae cauſae ſpem adeſſe comitem, Grot. Praef.</hi> was an old proverb, a good cauſe teacheth confidence; He hath the ſword of man and the ſword of the Spirit too, the expreſſe word of God, to aſſure him that he judgeth for God, and that God is <hi>with him in the judgement,</hi> 2. Chron. 19.6. Behold here are two ſwords, methinks he ſhould ſay it is enough; methinks if he know his own ſtrength, he ſhould not weigh the big looks of the ſons of <hi>Anak,</hi> he ſhould make no difference either in civil or criminall cauſes, betwixt the mighty hunters,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46942:11"/> that commit wickedneſſe with a high hand, and the cowardly lurchers that dare not ſhew their faces: he ſhould make no more of a powerfull oppreſſour, a valiant dueller, a gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant high-way man, or a mad ranter, then of a ſneaking cutpurſe. Once a ſling and a ſtone in the hand of <hi>David,</hi> and in the name of the Lord, triumphed over the long ſword and weighty ſpear of <hi>Goliah:</hi> and ſhall the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of God arm'd with ſword and ſpear, and coming forth in the name of the Lord too, be afraid of unarmed, naked, guilty, and therefore cowardly malefactours: ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he ſword of juſtice be afraid of the fiſt of wickedneſſe? <hi>Shall ſuch a man as I flee?</hi> ſaith <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> Iſa. 58.4. Shall the Miniſters of God be afraid of the ſlaves of Satan? Shall Gods be afraid of men? the worſt of men? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>et the Magiſtrates reverence themſelves, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hey expect reverence from others, and do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>othing unworthy the Maſter they ſerve, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he titles they bear. Indeed if this Miniſter of God leaves his Maſters ſervice, he leaves his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>wn ſafety; when <hi>Samſon</hi> leaves judging <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ael,</hi> and inſtead of watching in the chair, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eeps in <hi>Delilahs</hi> lap, his ſtrength ſoon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rts from him; but whileſt he is doing Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ork, he is ſtrong, and ſhould be ſtrong and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> a good courage, for God is with him.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:46942:12"/>4. His <hi>Duty, The Miniſter of God</hi> ordained for his ſervice. To inſtruct the Magiſtrate in the particularities of his duty, would be a bold and immodeſt undertaking, eſpecially in me, that know not what bounds are fixt him by the laws, and the tenour of his commiſſion. Mine is onely the eaſier task to lay down the generall rule; but to make application of it to particular caſes, is a difficult work, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter becoming the wiſdome and gravity of the Magiſtrate himſelf. The generall duty this title calls for is, that he mind Gods buſineſſe, that he execute judgement with all faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; <hi>for the judgement is Gods,</hi> Deut. 1.17. The Lord is Judge of all the world, his Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes are deſcribed by <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 9.7, &amp;c. <hi>He hath prepared his throne for judgement, and he ſhall judge the world in righteouſneſſe, he ſhall miniſter judgement to the people in uprightneſſe; The Lord alſo will be a refuge for the oppreſſed, a refuge in times of trouble,</hi> verſ. 12. <hi>When he makes inquiſition for bloud, he remembreth them, he forgetteth not the crie of the humble,</hi> or as <hi>Peter</hi> deſcribes him more briefly to <hi>Cornelius, He is no reſpecter of perſons, but in every nation he that worketh righteouſneſſe is accepted of him,</hi> Act. 10.34 This is Gods work. Let the Miniſter of God go and do likewiſe, let him ſhew himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:46942:12"/> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, as he is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a God upon earth, a living law. If he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard onely or chiefly his own honour, profit and advantage, as if that of <hi>Carneades</hi> were true in the worſt ſenſe, <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tilitas juſti prope mater &amp; aequi,</hi> That's onely juſt which is profitable, or as if he thought the people were intended onely for a beaſt for him to ride on: he may retain the name, but he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther performs the duty, nor ſhall receive the reward of the <hi>Miniſter of God,</hi> but of a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſervant that hath hid his Lords money, nay, that hath embezel'd it, that's worſe.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. His <hi>Dependance, The Miniſter of God,</hi> wholly ſubject to his diſpoſe. God hath not ſo inveſted his Miniſter in power as to ſtrip himſelf, but <hi>He ſtandeth in the congregation of the mighty, he judgeth among the Gods.</hi> Pſal. 82.1. Upon him the Magiſtrate depends in the riſe of his power, <hi>By me Princes rule, and nobles, even all the Judges of the earth,</hi> Prov. 8.15. Upon him he depends in the uſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of his power, <hi>By me Princes decree ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</hi> From me they have underſtanding to diſcern, and a heart to follow, and a hand to execute judgement and juſtice. Upon him he depends in the continuance of his power. God puts him out of Commiſſion and gives him a <hi>ſuperſedeas</hi> when he pleaſeth: <hi>Omne
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46942:13"/> ſub regno graviore regnum eſt.</hi> Whatever theſe petty Gods do, He that is higher then the higheſt obſerveth, and there be higher then they, Eccleſ. 5.8. <hi>Quàm diu bene ſe geſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint</hi> is the limit of their commiſſion. He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires ſtrictly, <hi>Do ye indeed ſpeak, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Oh congregation, do ye judge uprightly Oh ye ſonnes of men.</hi> He weighs theſe mountains in ſcales, and theſe hills in the balance; and if they be found too light, he writes upon them <hi>Belſhazzars</hi> fatall Motto, <hi>Mene, tekel, peres,</hi> if he ſtrip them not of their skins as the Emperour ſerved a corrupt Officer, he ſtrips them of their robes. Thrones, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, principalities and powers, are levelled with the touch of his finger, and all their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour laid in the duſt. <hi>Xerxes</hi> muſt know, though he be at the head of an army of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred thouſand men, that God will ſuffer none to be great but himſelf, as a wiſe Counſeller of his told him. <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compares Magiſtrates to <hi>ſpecies intermedia</hi> in Logick, which though it be <hi>genus reſpectu inferiorum,</hi> yet it is but <hi>ſpecies reſpectu ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riorum,</hi> they are publick perſons in reſpect of thoſe that are under them, but private ſubjects to the great King of heaven and earth; nay not ſo much ſubjects as ſervants, which ſpeaks greater dependance, <hi>the Miniſters of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:46942:13"/>6. His <hi>Accountableneſſe, The Miniſter of God,</hi> and therefore muſt expect one day to heare his own name called, and anſwer that unavoidable ſummons, <hi>Come give an account of thy ſtewardſhip, for thou mayeſt be no longer ſteward.</hi> Gods providence even in this world, is not ſo blind and indifferent in its outward diſpenſations, as we for want of due obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion make our ſelves believe. But in this life he generally ſhews his approbation or diſlike of his Miniſters, by rewarding the faithfull both with the bleſſings of his right hand, length of dayes, and the bleſſings of his left hand, riches and honour: and by puniſhing the unrighteous with all kinds of outward judgements; ſometimes miraculouſly, often remarkably, either in themſelves, or in their next poſterity, or in both. We might inſtance in <hi>Jeroboam's</hi> withered hand, <hi>Ahab's</hi> ruined houſe, <hi>Pilat's</hi> miſerable end; all the <hi>Herods,</hi> the <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and infinite more in the hiſtories of all ages, both ſacred and profane. The houſe that is built by oppreſſion and unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, hath the curſe of God hidden ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly in every part of it, which will cauſe the timber to rot, and the walls to moulder, and the foundation to ſink, except it be charm'd out by repentance and reformation, yea and ſatisfaction too, ſo farre as is poſſible. But
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46942:14"/> however the Miniſter of God ſpeed in this life, he muſt one day make his perſonall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance before that great tribunall, that knows no difference betwixt Prince and pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, the higher powers and the meaneſt vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, the talleſt Cedars in <hi>Lebanon,</hi> and the loweſt ſhrubs in the valley, but rewards to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man according to his deeds. Then he muſt give an account of his acquiſition of power, and of his exerciſe of power, whether he received the ſword at the hand of God, or ſnatcht it out of his hand, whether he uſed it or abuſed it. A good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> (ſuch as I hope! now ſpeak to) when he heares this may comfortably reflect upon himſelf, and ſay, <hi>Lord remember how I have walked before thee with an upright heart;</hi> Iſai. 38.3. but let a covetous, vicious <hi>Felix</hi> (for ſo <hi>Joſephus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports him) tremble to heare of judgement to come; For as that wiſe Carthaginian told the Senate, when their army under <hi>Hannibal</hi> had contrary to their league with the Romanes taken and ſackt <hi>Saguntum,</hi> I fear that the walls of <hi>Saguntum</hi> will fall down upon <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage:</hi> ſo the unrighteous Miniſter of God may juſtly fear (for it will moſt certainly come to paſſe) that the houſes he hath ruined by his perjury, falſe pleading, partiall verdict, or any other indirect means, will ſooner or later
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:46942:14"/> fall down upon his head, and cruſh him to pieces. I have done with the firſt part of the deſcription, the Magiſtrates office.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The ſecond Part.</hi> The end of his Office.</head>
                     <p>THere remains the end of his office to be ſpoken to, and firſt of the <hi>Finis cui,</hi> To whom he is the Miniſter of God for good. <hi>To thee</hi> that doeſt that which is good. If you ask what this good is, the Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers you, <hi>He hath ſhewed thee oh man what is good, and what doth the Lord require of thee, but to do juſtly, and to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God?</hi> Mich. 6.8. <hi>To thee</hi> therefore that walkeſt humbly with thy God, and dealeſt juſtly and mercifully with men: <hi>To thee</hi> that feareſt God and loveſt thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, <hi>he is the Miniſter of God for good.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>To thee</hi> that walkeſt humbly with thy God. If I were able to ſtate that great que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, How farre the Civil Magiſtrates power reacheth in matters of Religion, yet it would not be expected from me in theſe ſtreights of time. But if he conſider that all oaths and promiſes receive their ſtrength from Religion; that without Religion, juſtice and equitie are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:46942:15"/> but empty names, and as they ſay <hi>Epicurus</hi> taught, a meer humane compact without any foundation in nature: that Religion is, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>The very bond of all humane ſociety, and the foundation of laws:</hi> he muſt needs eſteem the defence, encouragement, and advancement of Religion, none of his leaſt concernments, as he is a Magiſtrate: beſides that as he is a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, he is bound to improve all his talents, and his authority among the reſt, for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the donour. The very profane Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians could not but take notice how much the Religion of the ancient Jews ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and enlarged the Commonwealth of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, <hi>Judaeorum juſtitia Religione permixta, incredibile quantùm coaluêre,</hi> ſaith <hi>Juſtin</hi> out of an ancienter authour. Religion and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe went hand in hand together, they were the two roots that nouriſhed that ſpreading vine. That part of Religion which is naturall, as that there is one infinite Deity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> declared in the firſt commandment; that he is inviſible, and above all things viſible, in the ſecond, that he obſerves orders, and judgeth all humane affairs, and knows their very hearts, in the third; that he is the Creatou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of the world, in the fourth; and thoſe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall concluſions, that ſpring from theſe, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="21" facs="tcp:46942:15"/> that he is to be loved, feared, honoured, ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, his name reverenced, his Sabbaths ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and the like; methinks ſhould chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge as much aſſiſtance from the civil ſword, as any other part of the law of nature what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. And as for the poſitive part of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, though I will not undertake preciſely to ſay, Thus farre the Magiſtrate muſt go and no further, yet ſure there muſt needs be a golden mean (God grant his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters may find it out) betwixt propagating of it by fire and ſword, and a careleſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference to the true Religion and the falſe; betwixt wracking of tender conſciences, and indulging all that pretends to conſcience: It concerns the Magiſtrate ſeriouſly to ſtudy the extent of his duty herein: For ſurely to take care of Religion, and religious perſons is one and a chief end of this Ordinance of God in the Text.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>To thee</hi> that dealeſt juſtly and merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with men, To thee that walkeſt uprightly, and workeſt righteouſneſſe, and ſpeakeſt the truth in thy heart, that backbiteſt not with thy tongue, nor doeſt evil to thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, &amp;c. as the 15. Pſalme deſcribes. It is eaſie to obſerve that the great Patrons of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, and confuſion, or of ſlack and ſleepy g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ernment (which is next to it) have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46942:16"/> been either ſeditious <hi>Corahs,</hi> that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not brook ſubjection, or bloudy minded <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaus,</hi> that wait for their fathers death, that they may be revenged on their brethren, or violent invaders of other mens properties, or diſſolute waſters of their own; whatever goodly pretences they make. <hi>Peter Martyn</hi> hits the true reaſon of their quarrel with the Magiſtrate, <hi>Vel quòd ſibi conſcii ſint rerum malè geſtarum, vel quòd mali ſint cultores juſtitiae;</hi> Either becauſe they are guilty of ſome unrighteouſneſſe already, or becauſe they intend it hereafter. Their great grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance is, that of the young Romane Gallants when their lawleſſe liberty was bounded by a ſtricter form of government brought in by <hi>Brutus, Legem rem ſurdam eſſe &amp; inexorabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, periculoſum eſſe in tot humanis erroribu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſolâ innocentiâ vivere;</hi> They cannot humour theſe deaf, churliſh, hard-hearted laws, they cannot ſtand upon theſe nice diſtinctions of <hi>meum &amp; tuum,</hi> juſt and unjuſt, they cannot live in theſe narrow incloſures; up with theſe hedges, down with theſe walls and mouns, and levell all into a wide unbounded cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian. It is no wonder ſuch as theſe ſpeak evi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of dignities, for the power is to them <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, a revenger for wrath, but to thee that loveſt righteouſneſſe, he is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:46942:16"/> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>the miniſter of God for good</hi> That's the firſt end of his office, <hi>Finis cui.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>We come now to the ſecond end. <hi>Finis cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus,</hi> for good, that is for thy benefit and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and that in five particulars, which I muſt but touch.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>In doctrinam,</hi> he is the Miniſter of God to thee for thy inſtruction in the wayes of peace an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> righteouſneſſe: <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons up this among the good fruits of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That whereas many innocent, &amp; honeſt minded men are yet to ſeek in the wayes of juſtice and righteouſneſſe: <hi>Poteſtas civilis illis pro Paedagogo eſt,</hi> The civil power tutours them in the art of living well.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>In Pacem,</hi> for thy peace and quiet, that <hi>ſummum bonum</hi> in politicks, the end of all civil diſcipline, yea and military too, for <hi>Sapientes pacis causâ bellu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gerunt; Saluſt.</hi> The daughter of heaven, the mother of plenty, the nurſe of learning and religion, the fruitfull womb of all outward bleſſings. This pretious oyl deſcends from the head of <hi>Aaron</hi> to the skirts of his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; This pleaſant dew flows from the top of <hi>Hermon</hi> &amp; <hi>Sion</hi> to the lower valleys, from the higher power to the people under their charge</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>In praemium,</hi> for thy reward, not onely thoſe generall rewards of priviledges, immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, liberties and the like, but riches, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:46942:17"/> and ſuch other ſpeciall encouragements, as are meaſured out in due proportions to the merits of well doers by the diſcreet hand of diſtributive juſtice.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>In tutelam,</hi> for thy defence and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard; That the Common wealth of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind may not be like that of beaſts and fiſhes, where the ſtronger devoure the weaker, and the worſe, the better; where the ſavage lion and the greedy wolf, and the ſubtil fox prey upon the innocent lamb: If once good men be left like ſheep without a ſhepherd, they'l ſoon be ſpoil d of fleece and fleſh, of eſtates and lives too.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. <hi>In vindictam,</hi> for thy revenge, that the injuries thou ſuffereſt may return upon the head of their authours, and that is thy good too, though not meerly as another mans e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; for the laws of Chriſtianity forbid us (in the Schoolmens phraſe) <hi>in malo cujuſquam acquieſcere,</hi> or <hi>alieno dolore quâ dolor eſt ſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ari,</hi> to take complacency meerly in the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of others; yet as it is a debt due to juſtice, a ſatisfaction to the laws of God and man, a terrour to other evil doers, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence a neceſſary means of ſafety and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation to mankind, ſo it is thy good and the publick good too. And thus the latter part of the verſe is a reaſon of this firſt part;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:46942:17"/> He is a revenger for wrath to him that doth evil, therefore the Miniſter of God to thee for good. I ſhall conclude all with a ſhort exhortation to each party in the text.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. To the Miniſter of God. My Lords, and who ever &amp;c. this title concerns: You ſee your calling, an honourable, but a weighty calling, beautified with many priviledges, but burdened with as many talents; Take the Pſalmiſts counſell which is properly directed to you, <hi>Serve the Lord with fear, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce with trembling,</hi> Pſal. 2.11. Serve the Lord becauſe you are his Miniſters, ſerve him with fear, becauſe you are but his Miniſters; Rejoyce in the dignity of your employments, but with trembling at the weight of it; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the motions of the heavens <hi>motus tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidationis</hi> is reckoned for one. Let the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of God rejoyce as a ſtrong man to run his courſe, but to all his motions let him adde this trembling motion. The judgement is Gods, and we know what a curſe attends doing the work of the Lord negligently and unfaithfully. I have not knowledge nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience enough to judge of the truth or falſhood of thoſe many clamorous complaints (that are already publick, or elſe I ſhould not name them) of the intricacie and obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the laws themſelves, of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:46942:18"/> and tediouſneſſe of Courts, of the mercinarines and double dealing of pleaders; of the exaction and extortion of Officers, of the partialitie and inſufficiencie of Juries, and the frequent indirectneſſe of all judiciall proceedings. It is likely they are groundleſſe calumnies and miſreports, at leaſt many of them. The world is apt enough to ſpeak e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil of every thing that is called the Miniſter of God, yet it is your wiſdome to conſider with that holy man, that the Lord hath ſent <hi>Shimei</hi> to curſe <hi>David;</hi> it is your wiſdome to interpret the reproches of men, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs of God, the complaints of men, the warnings and inſtructions of God. An ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my is fitly called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, one that teacheth a man his duty for nothing. The laviſh tongues of men thus underſtood may do you much advantage: but if you will follow the work of the Lord as becomes his faithfull Miniſters, they can do you no harm at all, they cannot ſtain your honour, for <hi>your judgement ſhall be to you as a robe and Diadem,</hi> as Job ſpeaks, Job 29.14. they cannot ſhake your power; for <hi>the throne is eſtabliſhed by righteouſneſſe;</hi> Prov. 16.12. you have two ſeals from the hand of God to bear you out: His broad ſeal, an outward viſible impreſſion of authority, and his privy ſeal,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:46942:18"/> the inward teſtimonie of a good conſcience.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To thee for whoſe good the Miniſter of God is ordained; the Apoſtles counſell in the former verſe is proper, Do that which is good; take heed of forfeiting that peace, protection, reward and encouragement, which the Providence of God, and the laws of men give thee a title to. To curſe the Sunne and to ſhoot up arrows at him, is mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in thoſe Indians that live under his ſcorching heat, but it were worſe in thoſe that live in temperate Climates, under his comfortable warmth and kindly influence. To quarrell with the Ordinance of God, and to curſe the Magiſtracy, is folly in guilty Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactours that live under the ſtroke of the civil ſword, but it were farre worſe in them that live ſafely under its guard. This were for the hands to mutiny againſt the belly, as it is in <hi>Agrippa</hi>'s parable. Your whole work as private men, is (in theſe full words of the Apoſtle) <hi>to live ſoberly, righteouſly and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this preſent world;</hi> and thus employed, you may in the ordinary courſe of providence, promiſe your ſelves (for God hath promiſed it) you ſhall have praiſe of the power. But if the Magiſtrate ſhould prove ſo unfaithfull to God, and unnaturall to man (which I hope your eyes ſhall never ſee) as to turn
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:46942:19"/> his ſword upon you merely upon account of your righteouſneſſe and religion, and of your Guardian become your deſtroyer. That which was the great ſupport of the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians will be yours, that your onely crime is Chriſtianitie. <hi>Bonum virum Caium Seium, tantùm quòd Chriſtianum,</hi> was proverbiall in <hi>Tertullians</hi> time, ſuch a one is an honeſt man, but onely that he is a Chriſtian. And <hi>if you ſuffer</hi> from him as Chriſtians <hi>for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe ſake, happy are ye,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth; whil'ſt he addes to your burden of afflictions, he addes to your weight of glory; and in this ſenſe alſo though againſt his own intention, and beſides the intention of the Text too, he becomes <hi>the Miniſter of God to thee for good.</hi> But God in mercy grant that no Miniſter of his may ever force the words to this interpretation.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46942:19"/>
                  <p>The Faithfull Steward, Briefly deſcribed in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preached at <hi>CAMBRIDGE:</hi> On the Commemoration of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ANDREW PERN. 1655.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>J. C.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi> Printed by the Printers to the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie.</hi> 1655.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:46942:20"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46942:20"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>LUKE 16.9.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Make to your ſelves friends of the mammon of unrighteouſneſſe.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His clauſe is the key of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going parable, and will ſerve to open to us all its ſeeming difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and abſtruſeneſſe. There we find an unjuſt ſteward, that had feathered his neſt with ill, gotten goods, yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by his Maſter, yea and propounded by our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt to our Imitation.</p>
                  <p>There are two Commentatours that ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome happen to agree in the ſenſe of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Maldonat,</hi> who yet meet pretty friendly in the application of this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. To them I referre you for the full reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of theſe hard ſayings: The text hath difficulty enough of its own to employ what time can be well ſpar'd from our intended practicall diſcourſe. I ſhall onely remind you of one generall rule of good uſe both here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd elſewhere in like caſes. That Scripture-parables, ſimilitudes and allegories are not to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46942:21"/> be ſtretcht upon the tenter-hooks, nor forc'd to an exact compliance with our over-nice and affected rules of rhetorick; a fault, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny learned men beſides <hi>Origen</hi> have been guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of. The parts of a ſimilitude are not like perfect planes that touch one another in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry point, but ſometimes, eſpecially in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture more like a globe on a plane that touch but in one. And of this kind is this compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon here betwixt the unjuſt Steward, and the faithfull Stewards of Jeſus Chriſt. They are like the unjuſt Steward onely in the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, not in the unrighteouſneſſe of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, in making themſelves friends, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not with other mens goods. Shall we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the diſciples of Chriſt to be ſo man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſonnes of <hi>Belial?</hi> Nay, ſhall we fancie Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> himſelf, as the poets their <hi>Jupiter,</hi> a partake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the filthy lucre and pleaſures of wretche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſinners? One that affects <hi>ſacrificium ex rap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nis,</hi> and will be brib'd to wink at their u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe for a ſhare in their prey? an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all this to make a parable more elegant, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> we conceit it, then was intended by the Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thour? God forbid! our Saviour compar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> himſelf to a thief elſewhere, and he com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pares his diſciples to thieves here, but no mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> intended an exact and through reſemblanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the latter, then in the former. His pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:46942:21"/> ſcope in ſhort is this. As the unjuſt Steward was wiſe in his generation, and made uſe of his Maſters goods, to provide himſelf a refuge againſt the time of his diſcharge: So be ye alſo wiſe in your generation with an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and heavenly wiſdome; and by ſuch noble, free, and generous acts of Chriſtian love, as becomes your holy calling, <hi>make to your ſelves friends of the mammon of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From the relation of theſe words to the parable foregoing, we might obſerve with <hi>Grotius, Non tam proprietarios nos eſſe quàm diſpenſatores.</hi> That our outward poſſeſſions are not our own to ſpare or ſpend as we pleaſe, to lay up for the feeding of our gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy eyes, or to laviſh out for the ſatisfaction of our brutiſh luſts; But there is a Lord over us, from whoſe mouth we muſt one day, and that ſhortly too, receive that dreadfull ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in the ſecond verſe, <hi>Come give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ount of thy ſtewardſhip, for thou mayeſt be no longer Steward.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to handle the words abſolutely and a part from the context will be work enough. And ſo they deſcribe to us the office of a Chriſtian Steward in three particulars. 1. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>harge of his office, <hi>The mammon of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eouſneſſe.</hi> 2. The duty of his office, <hi>Make
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46942:22"/> friends</hi> of it. 3. the benefit of his office, in the manner of expreſſion, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>friends to your ſelves,</hi> your debtours will become your friends, your beſt friends, that will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you into everlaſting habitations, as is explained in the latter clauſe of the verſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I. Particular.</hi> In the <hi>firſt</hi> wee'l conſider, firſt, the ſubſtance, and ſecondly the nature of the charge.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>ſubſtance</hi> is Mammon. Which is a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riack word, and ſignifies money, gain, riches, and all kind of worldly treaſure, as thoſe that have skill in that language inform us; though ſome think, and not without proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, that it might take its originall from the corruption of the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>theſaurus.</hi> This mammon our Saviour here ſuppoſeth committed to the charge of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, as the goods of their great Lord and Maſter. Though it be a groſſe ſuggeſtion of covetouſneſſe, for men to challenge all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſſeſſions to themſelves, upon the right of Saintſhip or prieſthood; (as we know who do) yet to make the profeſſion or diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpel inconſiſtent with worldly poſſeſſions, is a miſtake on the other hand, and as groſſe as the former. God no where approves, much leſſe enjoyns the voluntary poverty of ſullen Philoſophers, or ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46942:22"/> Mendicants. Is it the mind of God, think ye, that his Stewards ſhould rid their hands of their charge, and retire into a lazy ſolitude? Or is our Maſter ſo rigid and nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardly as to make all the trees of his garden forbidden fruit? To ſpread a table before us, and bind us up with thoſe ſtrict rules, touch not, taſte not, handle not? No; the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven is a miſcellanie of rich and poor, noble and baſe, Princes and peaſants; Ther's a poor <hi>Lazarus</hi> in the boſome of a rich <hi>Abraham;</hi> the great nurſing fathers and nurſing mothers, with their little babes in their arms. Though our <hi>Saviours</hi> outward condition was mean, and he was ſometimes worſe provided then the birds and foxes: yet a great diſciple of his, <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> was a rich and potent man. Religion forbids not to poſſeſſe the world, but to be poſſeſſed of it; not to have, but to ſerve mammon. Though that of the Apoſtle be true, 1. Cor. 1.26. eſpecially of the Primitive times, <hi>Not many mighty, not many noble are called,</hi> yet ſome there have been in all times, that have left glorious monuments of their Chriſtian love; and have demonſtrated, that liberalitie and magnificence are Chriſtian graces, as well as moral virtues.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Let us conſider the <hi>nature</hi> of this
<pb facs="tcp:46942:23"/> charge. It is ſtampt by our Saviour (who knew beſt how to eſtimate it) w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> a double character: a good character on the one ſide, make friends of mammon, it is improvable to a good uſe: and an evil character on the other ſide, the mammon of unrighteouſneſſe. It hangs here betwixt good and evil, the uſe and abuſe of it, as being of an indifferent nature, though ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inclining to evil through the generall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of our hearts. Let us firſt conſider the <hi>evil</hi> character, the Mammon of unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Some interpreters attending rather the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of the phraſe, then the exigency of the ſenſe, render it, Riches unjuſtly gotten; and moſt certain it is, that in this caſe according to the example of <hi>Zacheus,</hi> reſtauration ought to be made to the perſons injured, if poſſible, or elſe to the poore, who are their lawfull Attornies by Gods appointment. But yet there are two reaſons that forbid this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation here <hi>Firſt,</hi> We cannot think our Saviour would here ſuppoſe his diſciples (for to them he ſpeaks v. 1.) enabled by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, violence, and oppreſſion to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves friends. Nor ſecondly, would he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ill gotten goods, and them onely with theſe excellent properties of making friends, and furthering in any ſenſe their reception in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46942:23"/> everlaſting habitations. We may therefore ſafely conclude, that by mammon of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is meant riches indefinitely; not onely that which is the forbidden fruit of fraud and violence, but that alſo which is the lawfull fruit of our birth-right, or our indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie, or our intereſt in others. All worldly riches whatſoever, abſtracting from the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of acquiring them, are truly call'd the mammon of unrighteouſneſſe, and ſo <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> underſtands it, <hi>Mammona iniquitatis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitiae ſunt ſeculi omnes undocunque ſint:</hi> and that in a double ſenſe.</p>
                  <p>The firſt and moſt received is a <hi>paſſive</hi> ſenſe. The mammon of unrighteouſneſſe, that is, the object and matter of all unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, of injury and violence in the gathering, of pride and luxury in the ſpending. In which ſenſe our Saviour calls them thorns, Matt. 13.22. and <hi>Paul</hi> calls them a temptation and a ſnare, 1. Tim 6.9. <hi>Hierome</hi> applies that trite proverbiall ſentence to this place, <hi>Dives aut iniquus, aut iniqui haeres,</hi> as generally true. With him agree many of the ancients, and moſt of our modern divines too. <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos ſuos iniquitate involvunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Calvin. Maximè inveniuntur apud injuſtos, &amp; ab in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtis maximi fiunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Grotius.</hi> This mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon is that golden apple that puts the whole
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46942:24"/> world into diſorder and confuſion; and through the generall corruption of the ſonnes of men, becomes both the root and the fruit of their unrighteouſneſſe.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond is an <hi>active</hi> ſenſe. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, falſe, deceitfull, unfaithfull mammon, for <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, are obſerved to ſignifie the ſame in the Greek idiome. Though this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation at firſt view be not ſo plauſible as the former, yet there are two good argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of probabilitie for it. 1. They obſerve, that the Hebrew phraſe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>divitiae mendacii,</hi> lying, falſe riches, was much in uſe among the Hebrews in our Saviours time, and is often met with in their comments upon the Bible, and thence conjecture that this <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is onely an interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that phraſe. 2. The next verſe but one after the text ſeems to favour it. <hi>If therefore ye have not been faithfull in the unrighteous mammon</hi> (the ſame phraſe) <hi>who will commit unto you the true riches?</hi> where the oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwixt unrighteous mammon and the true riches ſeems to argue that by unrighteous mammon is meant falſe deceitfull riches: riches that deal unjuſtly and unfaithfully with us; for whil'ſt they tarry, they are but as empty husks to our belly, and as the rotten ſand to our
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46942:24"/> feet, and they will not tarry long neither; but in our greateſt need they take to themſelves wings and flie away. But whether this or the other be our Saviours meaning, moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his meaning is, to ſet a mark of ignominie and diſhonour upon that great idol Mammon, to deſtroy the magnificence of that <hi>Diana</hi> whom all the world worſhippeth, to caſt her headlong out of his fathers throne, and to debaſe her in the hearts and thoughts of his diſciples.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Let's conſider the <hi>good</hi> character of Mammon, <hi>Make friends,</hi> &amp;c. as bad as it is a good uſe may be made of it. There is a heavenly art of ſpiritualizing our worldly enjoyments. There is a way to clip the wings of riches, and to lay up even our earthly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in heaven. There is a divine Chymiſtry, that can extract the pureſt ſpirits from the moſt groſſe and feculent matter; that can ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance flints and pebbles to a neare reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of pretious ſtones. There is a lawfull craft of coyning your money over again, and adding the image and ſuperſcription of God to that of <hi>Ceſars.</hi> For to the pure all things are pure. The beaſt upon the altar differs not in kind from the beaſt in the ſlaughter-houſe; and yet the one is holy, the other common. It is the altar that ſanctifies the gift. A holy,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46942:25"/> gracious heart ſanctifies all that belongs to it. And this ſeems to me the moſt proper account of that ſpeech of our Saviour, which hath met with ſo many different conjectures, Luke 11.41. <hi>But rather give alms of all that you have, and all things are clean unto you.</hi> That to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere repenting ſouls, exerciſing works of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian charitie (which by a Synecdoche there, are put for all the fruits worthy of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as praying, elſewhere) to ſuch ſouls all things are clean, their very temporal enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are refined into ſpiritual bleſſings. But the way of improving this unrighteous mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon will appear more fully in the ſecond part of the text, which falls next under conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II. Particular.</hi> The duty of Chriſtian Stewards, <hi>Make friends,</hi> that is, Engage o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by a prudent and faithfull diſpenſation of the Mammon committed to your charge. For we are to conſider our ſelves under a double capacitie; private and publick. As par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, and as members of the whole world; of the univerſall Church, and of that particular Church, wherein our lot is fallen. Now though our great Lord &amp; Maſter allows our charity to begin at home, and to appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate to our private uſe ſuch a proportion of his bleſſings, as may enable us to the cheerfull
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46942:25"/> diſcharge of our duties: yet he expects our charitie ſhould not end where it begins, but freely flow forth, in hearty deſires to the whole world, and in reall expreſſions to ſuch a part of it, as the meaſure of our talents is able to reach. Thoſe that have had no other rule of judgement then the law of nature, and that in broken tables too, their own im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect and depraved underſtandings, have yet condemned a ſelfiſh narrow ſpirit as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy a creature, eſpecially of ſo high a rank as man is. They could take notice, that their great Creatour, though of a perfect ſelfſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency and independance, yet out of a free deſire of communicating his goodneſſe, gave a being to the whole creation, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues a conſtant ſtream of Goodneſſe unto all his creatures, that can never make him any real return. They could obſerve that the world it ſelf was <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the image and onely begotten of God. expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions pardonable in them (that knew none other of that name) and that it bears a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, as of his other perfections, ſo eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of his free and diffuſive goodneſſe. That the Sun with unwearied bounty poures out his light, heat and influence upon all he can reach, with tendereſt care cheriſheth them in his warm boſome; with admirable diſcretion
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46942:26"/> performs his yearly circuit from tropick to tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick, that all the parts of the earth may have their ſhare of his liberalitie. That the ſprings and fountains freely offer refreſhment to all that paſſe by. That all the elements, and their ſeverall mixtures, by a naturall ſelf-deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, reſiſt their own inclinations, and run the hazard of their private ruine for the ſafety of the univerſe. That heavy bodies mount up to heaven, and light bodies ſtoop to the loweſt room, rather then Nature ſhould receive the leaſt wound, yea or disfiguring ſcarre. Theſe and the like conſiderations made them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe <hi>Non nobis nati ſumus,</hi> &amp;c. That Man is not made onely for his own ſervice, but muſt caſt forth his virtue round about him. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that he is born to do good to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; That there is no monſter in nature ſo great as <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, A Schiſmatick from mankind, a man that is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from other men. This noble principle, though perhaps too much ſtain'd with ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and affectation of glory, hath prevail'd with many of them to ſpend their fortunes and lives for the ſafety of their countrey. The Grecian and Romane nations yield us many renowned examples hereof. And other nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have been inferiour to them rather in their records, then examples of the like kind.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46942:26"/> But we Chriſtians, beſides a clearer diſcovery of theſe natural arguments then the light of nature can afford, have incomparably more obligations upon us to enlargement of heart, then the heathens had, and therefore have the more to anſwer for, if we leſſe regard them. We know of a ſecond birth, of the love of God, greater to us then that of the creation, in ſending his onely begotten Sonne into the world, that whoſoever believeth in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life. We ſee (as it were) before our eyes the Lord Jeſus Chriſt denying, emptying, empoveriſhing himſelf (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) pouring out his warmeſt bloud with unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able pain and ſhame, and all to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf friends: Friends to receive grace and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from him, but not to make him the leaſt requitall, We have received the moſt pure and refined precepts of love, which not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Philoſophers, but even the Jews them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the greateſt Rabbies amongſt them were generally ſtrangers to. To denie our ſelves: To love our enemies: To return good for evil: To bleſſe them that curſe us, and pray for them that perſecute us and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitefully uſe us: To eſteem ſtrangers our neighbours. We have, or at leaſt pretend unto the ſpirit of the Goſpel, that free ſpirit, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46942:27"/> ſpirit of love, meekneſſe and compaſſion, That ſpirit of communion and fellowſhip. Under all theſe engagements ſhall we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract our hearts, and harden our bowels? Shall we confine our love meerly to our ſelves? Let's not be deceived, God will not be mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Whatſoever we ſow that ſhall we alſo reap. God is the true owner of all we poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe; and whatſoever we aſſume to our pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate uſe beyond the rules of ſobriety and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, will be judged embezelled, and without repentance exacted of us to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt farthing. To lay down the ſeverall rules and fit circumſtances of Chriſtian bounty, would be a work of time, and truly of no great neceſſitie. I think it was ſcarce ever known, that perſons of enlarged hearts, and ſincere purpoſes to do good, were yet at a ſtand for want of prudence to direct them in the manner of performance. I ſhall onely point out the ſeverall chanels wherein the bounty of Chriſtians uſeth to run; the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall occaſions they have laid hold of in all times, to diſcharge their charitie.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>For the honour and ſervice of Religion.</hi> Where ever Religion hath had a throne, ſhe hath alwayes commanded an honourable maintenance for her houſhold and retinue. Though indeed rather <hi>autoritate ſuadentis,</hi>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:46942:27"/> then <hi>poteſtate jubentis, Tacit.</hi> as was ſaid of the ancient Germane Princes, rather by a winning perſwaſive, then a rigid compulſive power. And this is one reaſon amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, why Religion is ſo much diſcountenanced by ſenſuall worldly men. They eſteem not ſpirituall things worth exchanging for a part of their carnall things; (with the Gadarens) they had rather part with Chriſt then their ſwine. They are content to loſe their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to ſave charges. If religion will put them to no coſt nor pains, perhaps they can endure it; but if it require either, they are as indifferent as that King of Denmark, <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demar,</hi> who lying under the Popes Interdict, ſends him this blunt meſſage, We received Our religion from thy Predeceſſours, which if thou wilt not ſuffer us to enjoy quietly, We ſend it thee back again, by theſe preſents. There hath been a time when Devout Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians have been willing to lay down their eſtates at the Apoſtles feet, to ſerve the Churches neceſſity. There hath been a time when ſuperſtitious Chriſtians have contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted beyond the Churches neceſſities. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the Venetian ſtate and others, have thought fit by ſevere laws to check their liberalitie, leaſt the Church ſhould ſwallow up the revenue of the Common-wealth.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46942:28"/> There is no feare of that extreme now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and we have grounds to hope the good providence of God will prevent the contrary. Though it be too manifeſt, The religious charitie of Chriſtians hath been much abuſed, yet ſurely the abuſe of their gifts may be reformed without their utter abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition. Drunkenneſſe may be ſuppreſs'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cutting down the vines, as that rigid lawgiver did. The houſe of God may be ſwept without a beeſome of deſtruction.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>For the encouragement of learning,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions handmaid, that hath for the moſt part flouriſhed with her miſtreſſe, and next to her is the greateſt honour and accompliſhment of a perſon or nation: The moſt beautifull ornament, the moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full inſtrument, that God vouchſafeth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſonnes of men. The onely remedie againſt barbariſme and ſavageneſſe. Yea ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citly commended by her very profeſſed ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies whileſt they are proud of that little learning they pretend to.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>For the upholding of their families.</hi> The bonds of nature are neither broken nor ſlackened, but exceedingly ſtrengthened by Chriſtianitie. Our great Apoſtle pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth him that provides not for his family, worſe then an infidel. And though he bore
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:46942:28"/> a tender affection to all the ſonnes of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> and became all things to all men for their advantage, yet his love to his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and kinſmen according to the fleſh ſo farre tranſports him, that he could even wiſh himſelf accurſed for their ſakes, Rom. 9.3.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>For the relief of the poore.</hi> That great ſacrifice of the Goſpel, ſo frequently and powerfully urged by the precept of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and his Apoſtles; ſo commended by the examples of all the Saints in all ages; ſo approved and exalted by the generall vote of the whole world; that the very naming it is ſufficient to prove it a principal ſtream of Chriſtian charity.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>For the publick good of the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> The beſt Chriſtians have alwayes been the beſt Commonwealths men. Indeed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious perſons both Jews and Chriſtians have been often accuſed for the troubles of Iſrael, That turn the world upſide down, that profeſſe a religion inconſiſtent with peace and civil government. But what ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals and groundleſſe calumnies theſe have been, Their very enemies, ſo many of them as have had the patience to ſearch out the truth, have acknowledged to the world; as might be prov'd by many inſtances, if it were needfull and ſeaſonable.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:46942:29"/>6. <hi>For the maintenance of humane ſociety.</hi> The Chriſtian name hath alwayes been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned for offices of courteſie and huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, as well as of compaſſion; and is as cleare from the imputation of ſordidneſſe, as of luxury and profuſeneſſe. Theſe, or ſome of theſe wayes (according to their abilities and opportunities) have the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Stewards of God laid out their earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly talents. Go you and do likewiſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>III. Particular</hi> is the <hi>profit</hi> or bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of their office, from the manner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. Make <hi>to your ſelves</hi> friends. And here the apologie of a late learned man in the like caſe is ſeaſonable. <hi>Ipſa virtus vilis hoc ſeculo ignoſcere mihi debet, ſi, quand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> per ſe contemnitur, ex utilitatibus ipſi pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium facio.</hi> If the beauty of this grace be not powerfull enough of it ſelf to enamour you, yet let her dowry tempt you. You will hereby make friends to your ſelves, migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty friends, that when ye fail, will receive you into everlaſting habitations, as it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows in the next words. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> indeed would have this latter clauſe underſtood of the Angels, and paraphraſeth the words thus. That when ye die, the Angels may receive you into everlaſting habitations. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers underſtand it indefinitely, and think
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:46942:29"/> it ſignifies no more then this. That when ye fail, ye may be received &amp;c. as elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where <hi>they ſhall call his name Emmanuel,</hi> Matth. 1. that is, his name ſhall be ſo called; and, <hi>this night do they require thy ſoul,</hi> that is, thy ſoul is required, Luke 12.20. But it beſt agrees with the parable foregoing, and with the contexture of the whole verſe, if we referre this <hi>(they)</hi> in the latter part to thoſe <hi>friends</hi> in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of the verſe, and ſo make the latter an exegeſis of the former. Make to your ſelves friends of unrighteous mammon, that when ye die, thoſe friends may receive you into everlaſting habitations. Not that all theſe friends of yours will be willing to receive you into happineſſe, ſeeing many of them may prove ungratefull and fall ſhort of it themſelves. Nor yet that any of them are able in their own perſons, and by their own power to receive you, for it is God that gives both grace and glory, and diſpoſeth of all places in heaven both at his right hand and at his left. Nor yet laſtly that they ſhall be your advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates and mediatours, fee'd by your cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable gifts to ſpeak a good word for you, and by their intereſt to obtain your rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption into heaven, as ſome groſſe Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:46942:30"/> collect from this place. But they may be ſaid thus to befriend you two wayes.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By being the objects and occaſions of thoſe pious and charitable works, which are the way to thoſe everlaſting habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And it is a familiar ſcheme of ſpeech, to aſcribe that to the object which properly belongs to the action. As parents honoured and obeyed may be ſaid to prolong our dayes. And the ſtone out of the wall, and the beam out of the timber, are ſaid to crie out againſt covetous perſons; So the backs and bellies, and ſoules of poore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed creatures, which out of an humble obedience to the law of Chriſt, and a ten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der compaſſion to your brethren; you have clothed, fed and refreſhed, will plead and that effectually upon the gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God, for your reception into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting habitations.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They may be ſaid thus to befriend you though not in their own perſons, yet by their ſureties. God himſelf and his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt, have engaged, and, if I may ſo ſpeak, entred bond with theſe poore debters of yours, to ſee your labour of love repaid with full intereſt: nay, to give you a recompence of infinite value, for that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:46942:30"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n it ſelf is worth nothing. God by his own promiſe hath made himſelf your debter, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that known ſaying of <hi>Auſtin, Fidelis dominus qui fecit ſe nobis debito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, non aliquid à nobis accipiendo, ſed omnia promittendo.</hi> You have it under the hand of the Holy Ghoſt himſelf, that giving to the poore is lending to the Lord. That en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining, clothing, feeding, viſiting the poore afflicted members of Chriſt, are ſo many good offices done to Chriſt himſelf, and acknowledged by him as his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall debts and engagements. So that prove your friends here ſpoken of never ſo diſhoneſt or unable in their own perſons, you need not feare the loſſe of your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, where the Lord himſelf is your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, and will ſtand your friend in their ſtead, to receive you into everlaſting habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
                  <p>This I conceive a true account of theſe expreſſions, But what ever miſtake theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures may be guilty of, the main ſcope and purpoſe of our Saviour in them is cleare and out of queſtion, and that is this. To declare this duty of making friends by a wiſe improvement of our earthly talents, to be of an abſolute neceſſity and certain ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie to everlaſting happineſſe: and that,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46942:31"/> in actual performance where there is abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, or however in willingneſſe of mind, which in want of abilitie, is the ſame in Gods acceptance, 2. Corinth. 8.12. For though without Phariſaicall pride and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancie, we cannot be ſaid to merit ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation by our good works, eſpecially as the Papiſts abuſe that phraſe contrary to the harmleſſe and well meaning uſe of it in ſome of the fathers. Yet that ſalvation depends upon our good works, taken in their due latitude, and in conjunction with their true principles of faith, and love, and humilitie of ſpirit; ſurely none that pretend to the knowledge and belief of the Scriptures, can noſſibly denie with any colour of reaſon. For the Scriptures do with one voice proclaim that the exerciſes of theſe graces is firſt, the way to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that good old way, trodden by all that ever travelled heaven-ward. And <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> that it is the meaſure of ſalvation, according to which every man ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his reward. And <hi>thirdly,</hi> that it is the preparative for ſalvation, fitting the faithfull ſervant to enter into his Maſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> joy. For grace makes way for glory, and happineſſe is nothing elſe but the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that love which is begun here
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:46942:31"/> This I take it, is true proteſtant do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. And therefore it is not our religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons fault, but our own, if the proteſtant name ſuffer under any deſerved imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of barrenneſſe and covetouſneſſe, and if it be, as ſome ſay, it is almoſt as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous for one kind of idolatry, as the Romane is for another. For our Religion moſt powerfully urges upon us all manner of religious, pious and charitable works, and teacheth their neceſſity and certain tendencie to everlaſting happineſſe, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the way to it, the meaſure of it, and preparation for it. I have not time to ſhew how the Scriptures abound in the proof of all theſe; or if I had, they are ſo plain, I need not. I ſhall onely adde a few words of exhortation, firſt, to the Stewards of God: and ſecondly to their friends made by their diſcharge of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. Neither are theſe alwayes diſtinct per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but ſometimes divers reſpects of the ſame perſons. For one man under divers conſiderations, and in ſeverall reſpects may be both a Steward and a friend, in the ſenſe of the text.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. You that are the Stewards of God, to whoſe charge the good things of this world are committed; you ſee before you
<pb facs="tcp:46942:32"/> your way into your Maſters joy. That more excellent way the Apoſtle ſhews us, 1. Cor. 12. Laſtly, more excellent then the beſt gifts; then propheſie, ſpeaking with tongues, underſtanding of myſteries, faith of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, yea more excellent then all other graces; <hi>For now remain faith hope and love, but the greateſt of theſe is love.</hi> If you are not yet arrived to that high and God-like degree of love, to do good and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate freely without any reſpect to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of reward, yet methinks, that ſincere, though fainter degree of love, to God and man, that warms the breaſt of every true Chriſtian, being encouraged with a moſt infallible aſſurance of an infinite and eternall recompence of reward, ſhould be ſtrong enough in you to provoke you to the exerciſe of all pious and charitable works, according to your abilities and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities. Neither let the Stewards of God flatter themſelves, that a negative faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe will ſerve the turn. That they have made uſe of nothing but their own; that they have not oppreſſed the poore, nor defrauded the hireling, nor devoured wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows houſes, nor robbed the communitie, nor injured any. Such account as this, though it be better then moſt men can make,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:46942:32"/> yet it will not paſſe at that great audit. For it proceeds upon a falſe ſuppoſition, that their poſſeſſions were their own, and not their Maſters, that they were Lords and not Stewards. The unfaithfull ſervant is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned out of his own mouth, not for imbezelling, but for not improving his Lords money. And there is a rich man in the next parable following the text, that is tormented with intolerable flames, not for oppreſſion, fraud and violence, but for immoderate enjoying his good things, and not commiſerating the wants of a poore lame beggar; for being clothed with purple and fine linen, and faring deliciouſly eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, and yet denying the crumbs-that fell from his table to diſtreſſed Lazarus. And though he had dogges to eat up his crumbs, dogges, that licked the poore mans ſores, and had more compaſſion in them then their maſter, yet this will not excuſe his chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh deniall of a poore mans requeſt. The right of dogges ceaſeth, when a poore man becomes their competitour. Let this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample be a caution to all the Stewards of God, that their backs, and bellies, their luſts and pleaſures, do not devoure all their good things, when the neceſſities of the Church, and the members of it call for a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:46942:33"/> ſhare with them. That they be not like thoſe ſonnes of pleaſure, Amos 6.5.6. <hi>That lie upon beds of ivorie, and ſtretch themſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their couches, and eat the lambs out of the flock, and the calves out of the midſt of the ſtall, that chant to the ſound of the viol, and invent to themſelves inſtruments of muſick, that drink wine in bowls, and anoint them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the chief ointment, but they are not grieved for the afflictions of Joſeph.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. You that by the bounty of others are engaged to be their friends, though their reward depends not upon your perſonal love and friendſhip, yet it becomes you to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe your ſenſe of your engagements, and to ſhew your ſelves in heart and affection their true friends. Neither doth the Lord in taking the debt upon himſelf, diſoblige you from your duty of reſpect and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to the inſtruments of his goodneſſe. But your friendſhip ought to ſhew forth it ſelf, at leaſt in theſe foure particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In a carefull and conſcionable obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of their precepts, and and all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of their pious and charitable works, ſo farre as conſiſtent with the laws of any higher power. God eſtabliſheth the houſe of the <hi>Rechabites,</hi> for obſerving the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of their father <hi>Jonadab,</hi> Jer. 35. and yet
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:46942:33"/> thoſe precepts were matters otherwiſe of an indifferent nature, as abſtaining from wine, and the like.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In a ſober and moderate uſe of their gifts, according to their pious intention. Pride and wantonneſſe, as they are no where more odious, ſo they are no where more conſpicuous, then in thoſe that lie upon other mens bounty. Nay, the leaſt appearance of vanitie in them (we all know) raiſeth ſuch ſcandals, as are not eaſily laid again. But by our Chriſtian ſobrietie and moderation, we ſhall either put them to ſilence, or at leaſt bear them comfortably.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In following their examples accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the meaſure we have received. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. They that have made us friends, have made us Stewards too: And if we be not rich to caſt in much, yet our mites are expected. The meaneſt of our condition cannot make us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of that glorious report the Apoſtle gives of the Macedonians, 1. Cor. 1.8. that the depth of their poverty abounded to the riches of their liberalitie. To ſpeak freely, It would better become our condition, if a little of our courteſie were turned into charity, and if ſomething were abated of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:46942:34"/> our mutuall friendly entertainments, to make to our ſelves friends according to the mind of our Saviour.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. In paying to them their due honour: to their perſons if alive; if dead, to their memorialls. However their names may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps be ſtain'd with reproches and ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, by the looſe and careleſſe tongues of others, yet it becomes their friends to ſpeak as they find: and to perfume their memory with honourable mention of their bounty and liberalitie. Whileſt <hi>Cham</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently beholds and reports his fathers nakedneſſe, let <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Japhet</hi> go back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and cover it. For though the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour done to the memory of thoſe whom God hath made inſtrumental for our good, be no real addition to their reward, yet it is a real expreſſion of our thankfulneſſe to God for them, and of our due valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the benefit we receive from him by their means, and may happily provoke others to the imitation of their worthy examples.</p>
                  <p>For which reaſons, give me leave as the preſent occaſion requires, to mention the name of that noble and free-hearted Benefactour both to this whole Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, and eſpecially to this adjoyning, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:46942:34"/> 
                     <hi>(Peter-houſe)</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ANDREW PERN. His bounty to this Colledge in adding a new foundation of two fellowſhips and ſix ſchollerſhips; in building our Library, and furniſhing it with a plentifull variety of choice books, in eſtabliſhing a Library-keepers place, and in many other works of great advantage. His happy and renowned endeavours for the honour and proſperitie of the Univerſitie in generall; for the vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, and enlargement of their privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges; his bequeſts of a yearly penſion to to the publick Library-keeper, and a box of ancient coyns and medalls of great value. But eſpecially his wiſe and ſucceſſefull pains in contriving and procuring that neceſſary Statute of the 18. of <hi>Queen Eliz.</hi> to turn the third part of our ancient rents into co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumony. To which both the Univerſities ow their comfortable ſubſiſtence ever ſince. His liberalitie to thoſe places in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, whereto he had relation, making them proviſion for a yearly Sermon, and diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to their poore. Theſe and many other worthy deeds of his deſerve of us, that his name ſhould be had in honourable remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance. But eſpecially they ſhould put us in mind of that gracious hand of God, that by this and many other the like inſtruments
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:46942:35"/> of his goodneſſe, hath made ſuch publick proviſion for the encouragement of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and learning, and hath given us in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular a ſhare in it. The Lord grant us ſuch a ſober uſe and faithfull improvement of theſe his mercies, that by the ſame good hand of providence, they may continue and dayly increaſe, both to the preſent, and to ſucceeding generations.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46942:35"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
